so let's see if we can do some dram
access scheduling to take advantage of
the fast page access that we can have
let's assume we have a data memory that
has 32 one bit arrays just like the one
we have seen before each array is one
megabit and it's organized as
two to the tenth rows
times two to the tenth bits per row
each array is a 16 megabit array
organized as 2 to the 12th
rows which is 4096 rows times 2 to the
12 bits per row
and the 24 bit
address
that we feed to this memory where bits
are numbered 0 through 23 is thus
divided by the theorem into a 12 bit row
address which is the upper bits of the
address and the column address which is
the lower 12 bits of the address of
course the processor when it issues this
24-bit physical address wants to access
a 32-bit memory location each chip is
fed this address and the 32 chips
together represent a 32-bit memory so
one chip for example might hold bit
number seven from all the words in the
16 mega word memory let's say we have
cash misses currently pending for the
following addresses let's assume that it
takes 10 nanoseconds to open a page
that it takes 2 nanoseconds to read
something from the row buffer once the
page is open and 5 nanoseconds to close
a page
these operations
how long do they take
if we do them in this particular order
and how long do they take if we are
allowed to reorder them
so that the time gets reduced